Finding Aid for University of Michigan admissions lawsuits collection, 1995-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Archived Admissions Lawsuit Website
  - March 31, 2003 capture
    - University of Michigan. Admissions Lawsuits Website. (Box 3)
      (original source http://www.umich.edu/~urel/admissions)
      - What's New February 2003-March 2003 (Box 3)
      - Press Kit revised, March 27, 2003 (Box 3)
  - September 16, 2003
    - University of Michigan. Admissions Lawsuits Website (Box 3)
      - What's New March 2003-August 2003 (Box 3)
      - FAQs November 2000-August 2003 (Box 3)
      - Legal Overview August 2002-August 2003 (Box 3)
      - Court Filings January 1999-July 2003 (Box 3)
      - Supporting Research January 1999-May 2003 (Box 3)
      - News Releases and Articles October 1997-August 2003 (reference index). (Box 3)
      - Statements by University Leaders and Others October 1997-August 2003 (Box 3)
      - Press Kits, Photos and Media Contacts revised, June 24, 2003 (Box 3)
      - En Espanol! December 2002-February 2003 (Box 3)
      - Archived Documents June 2002-February 2003 (Box 3)
  - First Amended Motion to Intervene February 10, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Reply Memorandum of Proposed Intervenors March 4, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Motion to Hear Oral Argument on Motion to Intervene June 5, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Motion for Reconsideration July 21, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Reply Memorandum in Support of Defendants' Motion for Reassignment or, Alternatively, for Designating Actions as Companion Cases July 29, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Opinion Designating Gratz and Grutter as Companion Cases, August 6, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Supplemental Memorandum in Support of Motion for Reconsideration August 14, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Defendants' Opposition to Plaintiffs' Motion to Certify a Class Action & to Bifurcate Liability from Damages September 10, 1998 (Box 22)
  - Motions of Proposed Defendant-Intervenors to Supplement the Record and to Stay District Court Proceedings May 19, 1999 (Box 22)
  - Exhibits in Support of Defendants' Opposition to Plaintiffs' Motion to Strike Any Testimony or Expert Opinions (including William Bowen) Based on Consideration of the College and Beyond Database (Box 22)
  - Appendix in Support of Defendants' Renewed Motion for Summary Judgment Regarding Plaintiffs' Claims for Injunctive & Declaratory Relief & Renewed Motion for Defendants Bollinger & Duderstadt for Summary Judgment on Grounds of Qualified Immunity July 15, 2000, 5 volumes (Box 22)
  - Appendix in Support of Defendants' Opposition to Plaintiffs' Motion for Partial Summary Judgment and Memorandum in Support of Defendants' Cross-Motion for Summary Judgment, 4 folders (Box 23)
  - Plaintiffs' Answer to Defendants' Petition to Appeal or for a Writ of Mandamus and Motion to Expedite Appeal May 9, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Petition for Permission to Appeal or for a Writ of Mandamus and Motion to Consolidate May 10, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Affidavit of Kirk O. Kolbo and Exhibits in Support of Plaintiffs' Renewed Motion for Partial Summary Judgment on Liability June 9, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Brief of National Association of Scholars as Amicus Curiae in Support of Plaintiffs' Motion for Partial Summary Judgment July 14, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Motion of National Association of Scholars for Leave to File Brief as Amicus Curiae in Support of Plaintiffs' Motion for Partial Summary Judgment July 14, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiffs' Motion to Strike Any Testimony or Expert Opinions (including William Bowen) Based on Consideration of the College and Beyond Database July 17, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiffs' Memorandum in Opposition to Defendants' two renewed motions for summary judgment & reply memo in support of Plaintiffs' motion for partial summary judgment on liability August 4, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Defendant-Intervenors' Response to Plaintiffs' Renewed Motion for Summary Judgment, August 10 2000 (Box 23)
  - Defendant-Intervenors' Response to Defendants' Motion for Summary Judgment as to Plaintiff's Claims for Declaratory & Injunctive Relief August 10, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiffs' Answer to Petition and Cross-Petition February 16, 2001 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiffs' Memorandum in Response to Intervenors' Motion for Entry of a Rule 54(b) or 28 U.S.C. 129(b) order (Box 23)
  - Proof Reply Brief of Appellees and Appellants July 2, 2001 (Box 23)
  - Final Brief of Appellees & Appellants July 30, 2001 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' Renewed Motion and Memorandum in Support of Defendants' Renewed Motion for Summary Judgment on Grounds of Qualified Immunity July 15, 2000 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiffs' Interrogatories to Defendant (Set I) December 24, 1997 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiffs' Request for Production of Documents to Defendants (Set I) December 24, 1997 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' First Set of Interrogatories to Plaintiff Patrick Hamacher February 13, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' First Set of Interrogatories to Plaintiff Jennifer Gratz February 13, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' First Set of Requests for Admissions to Plaintiff Jennifer Gratz February 13, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' First Set of Requests for Production to Plaintiff Jennifer Gratz February 13, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' First Set of Requests for Admissions to Patrick Hamacher February 13, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' First Set of Requests for Production to Plaintiff Patrick Hamacher February 13, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' Objections and Responses to Interrogatories #3-9 of Plaintiffs' Interrogatories to Defendants' (Set I) March 10, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' Objections and Responses to Plaintiffs' Requests for Production of Documents to Defendants (Set I) March 20, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiff Patrick Hamacher's Response and Objections to Defendants' First Set of Requests for Admissions April 1, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiff Jennifer Gratz's Responses and Objections to Defendants' First Set of Requests for Admissions April 1, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiff Patrick Hamacher's Objections and Answers to Defendants' First Set of Interrogatories April 3, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiff Jennifer Gratz's Objections and Answers to Defendants' First Set of Interrogatories April 3, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' Objections and Responses to Interrogatories #1, 2 and 10-14 of Plaintiffs' Interrogatories to Defendants (Set I) April 7, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiff Jennifer Gratz's Responses and Objections to Defendants' First Set of Requests for Production of Documents April 29, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Unopposed Stipulation for Protective Order Concerning Confidentiality May 27, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Plaintiff Patrick Hamacher's Responses and Objections to Defendants' First Set of Requests for Production of Documents April 29, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Defendants' Amended Objections and Responses to Plaintiffs' Requests for Production of Documents to Defendants (Set I) June 26, 1998 (Box 23)
  - Transcript of Oral Argument, Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals December 6, 2001, 2 folders (Box 23)
  - Plaintiffs' Petition for Writ of Certiorari Before Judgment to the United States Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit October 1, 2002 (Box 23)
  - Intervenors' Petition for Writ of Certiorari in Gratz, October 14, 2002 (Box 23)
  - UM Response to Plaintiffs' Petition for Writ of Certiorari Before Judgment to the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit October 29, 2002 (Box 23)
  - UM Response to Intervenors' Petition for Writ of Certiorari in Gratz, October 29, 2002 (Box 23)
  - Brief for Petitioners, U.S. Supreme Court January 16, 2003 (Box 24)
  - Brief for Respondents, U.S. Supreme Court February 18, 2003 (Box 24)
  - Brief for Intervenors Patterson, et al., U.S. Supreme Court February 18, 2003 (Box 24)
  - Petitioner's Reply Brief March 25, 2003 (Box 24)
  - U.S. Supreme Court Docket Gratz v. Bollinger, et al (Box 24)
  - U.S. Supreme Court Decision in Gratz v. Bollinger, June 23, 2003 (Box 24)
  - Plaintiffs' Reply Brief in Support of their Motion for an Interim Award of Attorney's Fees and Costs Pursuant to 42 U.S.C. sec 1988 October 1, 2004 (Box 24)
  - Plaintiffs' Reply Brief in Support of Motion to Allow Limited Discovery Related to Fees and Costs November 19, 2004 (Box 24)
  - Plaintiff' Motion and Memorandum of Law in Support of Motion for Class Certification and Partial Summary Judgment with Respect to Certain Nominal and Incidental Damages Claims; and for Certification of a Subclass to Determine Compensatory Damages Claims December 8, 2004 (Box 24)
  - Defendants' Response to Plaintiffs' Motion for Partial Summary Judgment on Liability and to Plaintiffs' Motion for Class Certification and Partial Summary Judgment with Respect to Certain Nominal and Incidental Damages Claims January 19, 2005 (Box 24)
  - U.S. District Judge Patrick J. Duggan's Opinion in Plaintiffs' Motion for an Award of Attorney's Fees and Costs January 27, 2005 (Box 24)
  - Plaintiffs' Combined 1) Reply Memorandum in Support of Motion for Partial Summary Judgment and Motion for Class Certification and Partial Summary Judgment with Respect to Certain Nominal Incidental Damages Claims; and 2) Memorandum in Opposition to Defendants' Motion for a Stay January 28, 2005 (Box 24)
  - Plaintiffs' Brief Regarding 1) Burden of Proof; 2) Legal Standard; and 3) Standing February 2, 2005 (Box 24)
  - Defendants' Response to Plaintiffs' Brief Regarding 1) Standing; 2) Burden of Proof; and 3) Legal Standard March 23, 2005 (Box 24)
  - Plaintiffs' Reply Brief Regarding 1) Burden of Proof; 2) Legal Standard; and 3) Standing April 6, 2005 (Box 24)
  - U.S. District Court Judge Patrick J. Duggan's Opinion in Plaintiffs' Motion Regarding 1) Burden of Proof; 2) Legal Standard; and 3) Standing August 5, 2005 (Box 24)
  - U.S. District Court Judge Patrick J. Duggan's Order Approving Settlement and Notice Plan, Decertifying Class, and Dismissing Case January 31, 2007 (Box 24)
  - District Court Amici Curiae Briefs
    - Attorney General Jennifer Granholm (Box 24)
    - College Board (Box 24)
    - State of Ohio (Box 24)
    - United States (Box 24)
  - Supreme Court Briefs
    - Brief for Respondents (Box 24)
    - Briefs in Support of Respondents Gratz
      - American Council on Education (Box 24)
      - American Educational Research Association, et al. (Box 24)
      - American Federation of Labor, et al. (Box 24)
      - American Jewish Committee, et al. (Box 24)
      - American Psychological Association (Box 24)
      - Amherst University, et al. (Box 24)
      - Authors of the Texas 10% Plan (Box 24)
      - Bay Mills Indian Community, et al. (Box 24)
      - Lt. General Julius W. Becton, Jr. (Retired Military) (Box 24)
      - Black Women Lawyers Association (Box 24)
      - Carnegie Mellon University, et al. (Box 24)
      - City of Philadelphia, et al (Box 24)
      - College Board (Box 24)
      - Columbia University, et al. (Box 24)
      - Representative John Conyers and other Members of Congress (Box 24)
      - General Motors (Box 24)
      - Harvard University, et al. (Box 24)
      - New American Alliance (Box 24)
      - New York City Council Speaker G. Miller, et al. (Box 24)
      - Northeastern University (Box 24)
      - NOW Legal Defense & Education Fund, et al. (Box 24)
      - Representative Richard Gephardt, et al. (Box 24)
      - Senators Thomas A. Daschle, et al. (Box 24)
      - Social Scientists Glenn C. Loury, et al. (Box 24)
      - State of New Jersey (Box 24)
      - States of Maryland, et al. (Box 24)
      - 3M, et al. (Box 24)
      - United Negro College Fund, et al. (Box 24)
      - University of Pittsburgh, et al. (Box 24)
      - Hayden Family (Box 24)
      - Howard University (Box 25)
      - Human Rights Advocates, et al. (Box 25)
      - Latino Organizations (Box 25)
      - Lawyers Committee for Civil Rights, et al. (Box 25)
      - Leadership Conference on Civil Rights (Box 25)
      - Massachusetts Institute of Technology, et al. (Box 25)
      - Media Companies (Box 25)
      - Members of the United States Congress (Box 25)
      - Michigan Governor Jennifer Granholm (Box 25)
      - MTV Networks (Box 25)
      - National Asian Pacific American Legal Consortium, et al. (Box 25)
      - National Coalition of Blacks for Reparations (Box 25)
      - National Education Association, et al. (Box 25)
      - National School Boards Association, et al. (Box 25)
      - National Urban League, et al. (Box 25)
    - Briefs in Support of Petitioners Gratz
      - Asian American Legal Foundation (Box 25)
      - Cato Institute (Box 25)
      - Center for Equal Opportunity, The Independent Women's Forum, and American Civil Rights Institute (Box 25)
      - Center for Individual Freedom (Box 25)
      - Center for New Black Leadership (Box 25)
      - Center for the Advancement of Capitalism (Box 25)
      - Claremont Institute (Box 25)
      - Duane C. Ellison (Box 25)
      - Law Professors (Box 25)
      - Michigan Association of Scholars (Box 25)
      - National Association of Scholars (Box 25)
      - Pacific Legal Foundation (Box 25)
      - Reason Foundation (Box 25)
      - State of Florida (Box 25)
      - United States (Box 25)
      - Ward Connerly (Box 25)
    - Briefs in Support of Neither Party
      - Anti-Defamation League (Box 25)
      - BP America Inc. (Box 25)
      - Equal Employment Advisory Council (Box 25)
  - Expert Reports
    - Lerner, Barbara (Box 25)
    - Raudenbush, Stephen (Box 25)
    - Rudolph, Jim (Box 25)
    - Silver, Jacob (Box 25)
    - Sugrue, Thomas (Box 25)
    - Trent, William (Box 25)
    - Welsh, Finis (Box 25)
  - Compelling Need for Diversity in Higher Education (Box 25)
  - On Appeal from the United States District Court for the Eastern District of Michigan (Duggan, J.), Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals, Joint Appendix, 9 volumes (Box 26)
- Video and Television Clips
  The Video and Television Clips series consists of VHS videotapes of presentations and television programs and news reporting about affirmative action in general and the U-M affirmative action lawsuits in particular. Tapes include off-the-air recordings of local and national new programs and some coverage of Supreme Court proceedings. The tapes were assembled by the University of Michigan News Service.
  - General Affirmative Action
    - "Michigan Alumni Video 1991" January 1, 1991 (Box 27)
      (President James Duderstadt speaking of the Michigan Mandate during his statement.)
    - ABC "World News Tonight" "American Agenda" segment on affirmative action and college admissions. July 20, 1995 (Box 27)
    - Detroit WXYZ-TV "Spotlight on the News" with President Lee Bollinger, discussion of affirmative action after third commercial break September 14, 1997
  - Admissions lawsuit coverage
    - ABC "World News Tonight" December 2, 1997 (Box 27)
    - "NBC Nightly News" December 3, 1997 (Box 27)
    - Detroit WXYZ-TV "Spotlight on the News" with Provost Nancy Cantor,. December 13, 1998 (Box 27)
    - "CNN & Company" U-M student Erika Dowdell part of a discussion of affirmative action and racial preference March 9, 1997 (Box 27)
    - "Affirmative Action: Where Do We Stand?," September 29, 1999 (Box 27)
      (public forum in Michigan League with a panel including President Mary Sue Coleman, General Counsel Marvin Krislov, Provost Nancy Cantor, Law School Dean Jeffrey Lehman and lawyer John Payton.)
    - CBS "60 Minutes" story on scholarships for white students at Alabama State University, Fall 1999 (Box 27)
    - Detroit WXYZ-TV "Spotlight on the News" with Law School Dean Jeffrey Lehman (Box 27)
    - NBC "Today" includes a segment with admissions lawsuits plaintiff Jennifer Gratz and U-M Vice President Walt Harrison (Box 27)
    - PBS "NewsHour with Jim Lehrer" appearance by law Professor Rebecca Eisenberg July 6, 2000 (Box 27)
    - CBS "60 Minutes," "Negative About Affirmative Action?" October 29, 2000 (Box 27)
      (two copies, one transcript)
    - CBS "60 Minutes" in which U-M philosophy Professor Carl Cohen's attitude toward, affirmative action is explored July 8, 2001 (Box 27)
    - "One2One: A Conversation with Mary Sue Coleman," Sept 5 2002 (Box 27)
      (produced by Michigan Television and Michigan Radio, affirmative action discussed about 10 minutes in)
    - U-M Admissions Lawsuits: An Update," September 18, 2002 panel discussion and question-answer session in Mendelssohn Theater (Box 27)
    - "CBS Evening News," President Mat Sue Coleman on the admissions lawsuits December 2, 2002 (Box 27)
    - MSNBC "Nachman," December 3, 2002 (Box 27)
      (Law School Dean Jeffrey Lehman among guests in a discussion of admissions lawsuits)
    - CNN-TV "Lou Dobbs Moneyline" "university of Michigan Admissions December 9, 2002 (Box 27)
    - ABC "World News Tonight," admissions lawsuits story with U-M General Counsel Marvin Krislov near end of program January 15, 2003 (Box 27)
    - Detroit WXYZ-TV evening newscasts, including coverage of Supreme Court arguments on U-M affirmative action procedures. April 1, 2003 (Box 27)
    - "NBC Dateline: A Question of Fairness" June 6, 2003 (Box 27)
      (two copies)
    - News coverage from several programs of the Supreme Court decision in the admissions lawsuits June 23-24, 2003 (Box 27)
      (two tapes, one 4 min. 50 sec., the other 7 min. 45 sec.)
    - CNN, NBC, BBC coverage of the Supreme Court decision in the admissions lawsuits, June 23-24 (Box 27)
      (from communications Lecturer Anthony Collings; includes a log of "CNN Sunday night")
    - Michigan at Risk," "Affirmative action on Trial," August 26, 2003 (Box 27)
      (30-minute documentary (including U-M officials and students) followed by a discussion including U-M General Counsel Marvin Krislov)
      (3 copies)